Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, a sad תשעה באב Tisha B'Av everybody.
We pick up today's דף daf is
קעא, kuf ayin aleph, 171, and we pick up at the top
of קעא. kuf ayin aleph. And the issue was what do you
do if somebody has written a
שטר חוב shetar chov of a debt and part of it was
paid off, like a thousand dollars and the guy pays 200, what
are you supposed to do? So there is a debate in the
משנה mishna where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you replace it with
the שטר shetar of 800 and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says you
write a שובר. shovar.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't like writing a שובר shovar because
it puts new responsibility on the לוה loveh to watch the שובר.
shovar. And רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's why רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
excuse me, doesn't like writing the שובר. shovar. And רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi doesn't like writing a new שטר shetar because he said that
writing a new שטר shetar somehow will hurt the interests of the
מלוה. malveh. It's not clear why it will hurt the interests of
the מלוה, malveh, but the best explanation is the assumption is that
the new שטר shetar that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is promoting is
one that would be dated as of today and that would really
hurt the interests of the
מלוה malveh because then he would lose all of the liens from
the original time of the loan. So that's why רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi said I'd much rather there be a שובר shovar and we
put that responsibility on the לוה loveh than hurt the interests of
the מלוה. malveh. So comes along the גמרא Gemara and says in
the name of רב Rav that actually we write a new שטר
shetar but we write it from the time of the original loan,
which is the best thing, right, it doesn't hurt the interests of
the מלוה malveh and so on. Okay, and that and presumably understood
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as the simple reading would be that it
would only really be of the new time and רב Rav is
saying no, no, no, it's from the time of the loan.
So let's actually read that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's reread this
גמרא Gemara from the middle of קע עמוד ב. kuf ayin amud
bet. So
let's just start from the משנה. mishna. We'll do it very quickly.
We did it yesterday but it's so short and anyway so let's
do it. מי שפרע מקצת חובו, Mi shepara miktzat chovo, רבי יהודה
אומר יחליף, Rabbi Yehuda omer yachalif, so you create a new שטר.
shetar. רבי יוסי אומר יכתוב שובר, Rabbi Yosi omer yichtov shovar, you
write a receipt. אמר רבי יהודה נמצא זה צריך להיות שומר שוברו
מן העכברים, Amar Rabbi Yehuda nimtza zeh tzarich liyot shomer shovaro min
haachbarim,
that's not fair to have to base it on the שובר, shovar,
the לוה loveh have to watch his שובר shovar and if he
doesn't watch his שובר shovar he'll have to pay the full debt.
אמר לו רבי יוסי, Amar lo Rabbi Yosi, כך יפה לו, kach
yafeh lo, that's appropriate. Maybe it's appropriate because, you know,
it's his responsibility to pay off the debt. ולא ירע כחו של
זה, velo yera kocho shel zeh,
why should you compromise, why should you hurt the interests of the
מלוה? malveh? Again, presumably the hurting of the interests of the מלוה
malveh is presuming that the new שטר shetar of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is from the new date. So let's take a look. אמר
רב הונא אמר רב אין הלכה לא כרבי יהודה ולא כרבי יוסי,
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav ein halacha lo keRabbi Yehuda velo keRabbi
Yosi,
we don't rule either these ways, neither a שובר shovar nor a
שטר shetar from the new date. אלא בית דין מקרעין את השטר,
ela bet din mekarchin et hashetar, בית דין bet din tears up
the old one וכותבין לו שטר אחר מזמן ראשון. vekotvin lo shetar
acher mizman rishon. You write it from the original date. That makes
a lot of sense, okay, and he apparently understood like it seems
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi understood that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was advocating
only a שטר shetar as of today and רב Rav says no,
no, no, we rewrite the original שטר shetar from the original date
with the new amount. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרב הונא ואמרי לה
רב ירמיה בר אבא לרב הונא אי שמיעא ליה לרב, Amar leh
Rav Nachman leRav Huna veamrei leh Rav Yirmiya bar Abba leRav Huna
i shemeia leh leRav, הך ברייתא ha braita דתניא, detanya, had רב
Rav heard the ברייתא braita that we're going that and that actually
it recaps the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi and it clarifies that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
it meant the original date. דתניא Detanya with a ברייתא braita teaches
עדים מקרעין את השטר, edim mekarchin et hashetar, עדים edim tear up
the שטר shetar וכותבין לו שטר אחר מזמן ראשון, vekotvin lo shetar
acher mizman rishon, and they write a new שטר shetar from the
original date. So you, רב, Rav, you got so worked up and
you had to say no, no, the שטר shetar has to be
from the original date, it's not like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
There's a ברייתא braita that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says exactly that.
He clarifies his position that it's the original date. הדר ביה. Hadar
beih. What does it mean worked up? Yeah,
so had רב Rav heard that he would have retracted, he wouldn't
have felt the need to say I'm פוסק poskening a third position
because it would have been clear to him that even רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says the original date and he would have just said
we פוסק posken like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אמר ליה, Amar leh,
one minute, שמיעא ליה, shemeia leh, he heard that ברייתא braita ולא
הדר ביה, velo hadar beih, but he didn't retract. He still felt
that he had to פוסק posken a position that was not represented
in the משנה. mishna. Why isn't he just פוסק poskening רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda now that we know that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
the שטר shetar is from the original date? Because no, the difference
is that רב Rav here is being stricter. רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
claim is says עדים edim tear up the שטר shetar and רב,
Rav, the חידוש chiddush of רב Rav is not מזמן ראשון. mizman
rishon. This ברייתא braita clarifies that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
that. The חידוש chiddush of רב Rav is if you're going to
do it from the original date then you're going to need a
בית דין bet din to do it. בשלמא בי דינא אלימא לאפקועי
ממונא, Bishlama beidina alima leafkuei mamona, בית דין bet din has the
power they can you know. Extract money from people, they can say
הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beis din hefker. So if they want
to create a new שטר shtar from an earlier date they're entitled
even though it's not today and even though normally such a thing
would be like a שטר מוקדם. shtar mukdam. Okay, אלא עדים שעשו
שליחותן חוזרים ועושים שליחותן? ela eidim she'asu shlichusan chozrin v'osin shlichusan? But
the witnesses once they signed on the original שטר shtar and they've
done what their job was, how are they entitled to write a
new שטר? shtar? If you were to write a new שטר shtar
as of today, no problem because the same way if let's say
I paid $200
of the $1,000 I owed Michael, the same way I could write
now borrow $800 from Michael since we both agree I paid up
the 200, we both Michael you know what are we going to
do I want a new we both want a new שטר shtar
that says 800. So you know so we can basically say let's
pretend like I paid up the full debt and I borrowed a
new $800 right now. So we can make a new שטר shtar
of $800 as of today. You don't need any special power to
make a שטר shtar as of today if the מלוה malveh and
the לוה loveh are in agreement. Okay, that's no big deal. But
if you're going to say מזמן ראשון, mizman rishon, you're going to
create a שטר shtar that's going to effectively create liens from a
year ago, okay, and that is not something that witnesses and the
מלוה malveh and לוה loveh can all do together. You're not allowed
to make a שטר shtar that's earlier dated. So that needs a
בית דין beis din to do it. If we're going to do
the earlier date we need a בית דין beis din to do
it. Yes, question?
So the מלוה malveh might be motivated to agree to like write
the new שטר shtar as of today and give up the liens
because he gets some money payment up front now.
Yeah, but but that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi but that's what
יהודה Yehuda
that's presumably you know hard to imagine like the מלוה malveh would
say no way buddy I'm going to give you a receipt for
your $200 I'm not going to lose my which is what רב
Rav you know which is what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says in
the משנה. mishna. There is nobody who there is no good argument
that there's no way it would be fair to demand a new
שטר shtar as of today's date, which is why the ברייתא braita
clarifies that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda new שטר, shtar, you know, which
is what that was רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi critique, but it's hard
to imagine how רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could advocate for that,
which is why רב Rav
said and the ברייתא braita clarified that
even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says it's of the original date.
Michael you had a question before? Yeah, I mean, but this just
seems like if anything it's not I
don't see
the big deal about why you need a בית דין beis din
involved.
Because, okay, because say that why? Why why would it not be
a big deal even though it's a you're writing an earlier date
and all it is is is you know for now less you're
just...
Right. So this is a point that תוספות Tosfos makes which is
it's a big difference if we were to try to create liens
that didn't exist, okay, and we were to say well we're a
court we can do it
we're going to create liens of a year ago that don't exist.
These liens do exist. We are just creating a new שטר shtar
to testify to them. Normally you need the שטר shtar to create
the liens, okay, but the liens existed because we have an existing
שטר shtar that does it, okay. So this שטר shtar is really
just to testify to a fact that is actually true. So what
is the big deal? Okay, so תוספות Tosfos acknowledges that. תוספות Tosfos
says exactly that point and תוספות Tosfos says you're right. It's not
like you it's not like if witnesses did it it really wouldn't
be valid especially if the same witnesses. We saw me borrow $1,000
a year ago, the witnesses saw them, so now they're writing that
I owe you 800, okay? It's not you know it's like בכל
מאה מנה bechol meah maneh it's not a lie that I owe
you 800 I originally owed you 1,000 or whatever. You know maybe
they shouldn't say I borrowed 800 but what they could say they
saw דב Dov borrow you know money from Michael and he owes
him $800 and predate it and that's all true and they're just
making a new שטר shtar based on what they saw before but
they're not creating any new liens. So תוספות Tosfos says you're right.
The problem is is that it's opening it's the old
slippery slope opening the door. If to just allow עדים eidim on
their own to write a predated שטר shtar is very bad policy,
okay? Because this is a special case the מלוה malveh and the
לוה loveh together agree we're going to predate it, it was paid
up, etc. But you know once you sort of let people you
know you know the inmates run the asylum you know once you
let people sort of you know do their own thing without the
supervision of בית דין. beis din. Now normally you can you don't
need a בית דין beis din to write a שטר shtar but
to predate a שטר shtar that's dangerous stuff. And even though here
it's okay this is the way תוספות Tosfos reads it, we would
not allow רב Rav is saying we would not allow that to
be done without the auspices of a בית דין. beis din. Okay
so that's the way we did not in a sort of fundamental
way it's not possible, the גמרא Gemara sounds like it's more fundamentally
not possible, תוספות Tosfos says more of a policy issue we would
not allow it. But it's a very good question. The other point
that is worth noting I'll just mention briefly this long תוספות Tosfos
here raises the question about remember the גמרא Gemara before about a
שטר shtar that was being erased?
And it says we go to and we sort of rewrite it
and whatever, you know, we sort of get a בית דין beis
din to rewrite it. So תוספות Tosfos asks the question is that
שטר shtar that was in the process of being erased and that
we're rewriting going to be from... the earlier date or from the
present date? Now, of course logically it would be from the earlier
date, that would be a terrible loss to the מלווה malveh if
it was, and there's nothing in the גמרא Gemara that indicated it
would only be as of today, it sounds like it's a full
replacement. But תוספות Tosfos says there's one thing that makes that case
worse than this case.
What's the—no,
what makes it worse is that the לוה loweh isn't agreeing. Michael
comes with his שטר shtar for a thousand dollars to בית דין
Beis Din and says this is being erased, I want it rewritten,
and I'm saying I don't agree. Why do I not agree? What
do you mean why do I not agree? I don't want another
שטר shtar written. Like, I don't authorize it, okay? And normally a
שטר shtar can't be written against me without me authorizing the עדים
eidim to write the שטר. shtar. Okay, that's what we called before
דעת מתחייב. da'as mis'chayiv. The side that is being hurt by the
writing of the שטר shtar has to authorize its writing. Okay, so
תוספות Tosfos says if I don't authorize it, on the one hand,
it's like we just said, you're not creating anything new, you're just
re-testifying to something that was true and already existed. But תוספות Tosfos
does say it's a little trickier there because the לוה loweh isn't
authorizing it. So there maybe you need a בית דין Beis Din
in a more substantive way. If it's being done without the authorization
of the לוה, loweh, even though you're not creating anything new and
you're just rewriting something etcetera, maybe every creation of a שטר shtar
to be a legitimate שטר shtar needs דעת מתחייב, da'as mis'chayiv, needs
the authorization of the injured party. And therefore that, even though again
the liens exist, that maybe needs a בית דין Beis Din at
a substantive level. And maybe there, if you only had עדים, eidim,
right, you know, there would be no way you could write it
at an earlier date. But this שטר, shtar, which is done by
both parties agreeing to it—of course I want a new שטר shtar
of eight hundred. I don't want him to have a שטר shtar
that says a thousand. I'd much rather, right, I'd rather have him
have a שטר shtar that says eight hundred than him have a
שטר shtar that says a thousand and me have a receipt. So
I'm authorizing the עדים. eidim. Both sides are authorizing. That's why it's
possible that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says you don't need a בית
דין, Beis Din, and רב Rav says no, nevertheless you need a
בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, but the way תוספות Tosfos explains it
is it's not because in principle you need a בית דין, Beis
Din, it's because it's bad policy and you would need a בית
דין Beis Din to write an earlier dated שטר shtar and you
need a בית דין Beis Din to authorize it. Okay, but here
since they're not creating anything new and both sides are agreeing to
have the new שטר shtar written, it makes it much easier to
do.
Okay, yeah, that תוספות Tosfos on אין הלכה כרב יהודה. ayn halacha
k'Rav Yehuda.
The big תוספות Tosfos on ק"ט עמוד ב'. kuf tes amud beis.
The big one. Yeah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ולא—now v'lo is that really true, that עדים eidim cannot go
ahead and rewrite a שטר shtar that they've already written? והאמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, ve'ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says in the name of רב: Rav: עדים כותבים אפילו עשרה שטרות
על שדה אחת. Eidim kosvin afilu asara shtaros al sadei achas. The
same רב Rav here who says you need a בית דין Beis
Din says that עדים eidim can rewrite, you know, even ten deeds
on the same plot of land. So how can they do that?
רב Rav says you need a בית דין Beis Din to rewrite
a שטר. shtar. So now רב יוסף אמר בשטר מתנה, Rav Yosef
amar b'shtar matana, ורבה אמר בשטר שאין בו אחריות. v'Rabba amar b'shtar
she'ein bo achrayus. Ah, that's different, because there there is—we're talking about
a case where there are no
liens. Right? A normal—it's just a deed. Now, but a deed normally
hurts other people potentially because that gives me liens that if the
land is taken from me I can get reimbursed. Okay, but there
are two versions of the one that does not have liens. One
is if somebody gifts me land. Yes, you could explicitly write liens
into a gift, but normally, the default, we would not assume that
a gift is I love you so much I'm giving you this
as a gift and I'm promising to reimburse you if it gets
taken. Okay, that we're not going to assume. We're not going to
assume the liens in a שטר shtar that's a gift of land.
Or number two, it explicitly excludes liens. It says here it is,
I sold you this plot of land, but let it be known
that I am not providing you with any, you know, with any—I'm
not taking any אחריות, achrayus, I'm not taking any responsibility if it
gets taken, I am not going to—not only not liens, no אחריות,
achrayus, no insurance. I am not—you're not going to get reimbursed from
me if it gets taken from you. Okay, so in those two
types, either by a gift שטר, shtar, by default there's no—there's no
insurance, or it explicitly said there's no insurance, in those types of
cases you can go ahead and rewrite because nobody is hurt. So
even though you're writing it from a year ago, let's say, we
wouldn't say, oh my God, you're opening the door to write a
שטר מוקדם. shtar mukdam. It's not a problem of a שטר מוקדם
shtar mukdam unless there are liens. The problem of a pre-dated שטר
shtar is you're going to cheat out all of the innocent people
who bought the land in the interim and you're going to claim
you have liens when you don't have liens. But a שטר shtar
that has nothing to do with the liens and the witnesses saw
the actual original thing, they can write substitute שטרות shtaros without the
presence of a בית דין. Beis Din. One minute, now תוספות Tosfos
says: what do you mean? Didn't we have a discussion earlier about
a problem of writing substitute שטרות, shtaros, you know, and maybe even
without a concern of liens? Like maybe the guy's having a whole
trick going on there? Right? So if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosfos, this little תוספות, Tosfos, כותבין אפילו. kosvin afilu. ...עשרה שטרות,
asara shtarot, he says אם תאמר למאי דסלקא דעתך דבאחריות מיירי, im
tomar lemai desalka datach debachrayos mairi, and when certainly when we thought
we were talking that there were liens, ככי הדאמרן לעיל, kechi ha
de'amran le'eil, אבל בשאר מקח וממכר כותבין חוץ מאחריות שבו. aval beshar
mekach umimkar kosvin chutz me'achrayos shebo. How could we even have thought
you're going to write a substitute שטר shtar with liens, you know,
before we had all these concerns about people having these schemes and
so on? So he says ויש לומר דאהא דרישון דהוא אמר אבד
שטר חובי וחיישינן דילמא טרפא דטרף. ve'yesh lomar de'aha de'rishon de'hu amar
avad shtar chovi ve'chaishinan dilma traifa detaref. There we were concerned that
he didn't really lose it and it was a scheme. אבל הכא
מאי דבידוע לנו שנאבד או ראינו שנשרף. aval hacha mai debe'yadu'a lanu
sheneevad o reinu shenisraf. He says this is not a case of
a concern of a scheme. We actually saw the original שטר shtar
being destroyed, like black at that point. The only question here is
not could it be abused, but are the עדים eidim authorized to
write a replacement שטר? shtar? And here the answer is yes. Everybody
would agree that the עדים eidim who saw the thing can write
replacement שטרות shtarot if there's no אחריות achrayos and there nobody is
being, you know, hurt or there's no א alef nobody's being hurt
and ב bais
right there's no threat of of allowing people on their own to
write a שטר מוקדם. shtar mukdam. But a שטר shtar that has
liens in it, we do not Rav says I do not want
to allow people on their own, עדים eidim on their own to
do that. That is just big slippery slope for שטרי מוקדם. shtarei
mukdam. That has to be under the auspices of בית דין. beis
din. Yes, so you had a question.
When there's a sale of a piece of land in the גמרא,
Gemara, the גמרא Gemara assumes in general that there's אחריות achrayos or
that there's no אחריות?
achrayos? Yes, well that was the earlier discussion. אחריות טעות סופר achrayos
tayus sofer or לא טעות סופר. lo tayus sofer. But the general
assumption is טעות סופר. tayus sofer. There's assumed to be אחריות. achrayos.
Yes, but you're right, there's a difference between אחריות טעות סופר achrayos
tayus sofer in a in a loan as opposed to אחריות טעות
סופר achrayos tayus sofer in a sale of land. Why? But there
the general assumption there too is is אחריות טעות סופר. achrayos tayus
sofer. Yes. Which date do they use?
The original date. But it's not so but the point but the
point being is we don't think this is going to be a
slippery slope towards שטר מוקדם shtar mukdam because even though it's predated,
it's predated on an innocuous type of a שטר. shtar. Okay, a
שטר shtar that doesn't have liens is not a is not a
שטר shtar that it really is it matters to predate. Okay, so
therefore, there we're not afraid. But a שטר shtar that it has
liens and is predated, even though in this case it makes sense,
the מלווה malveh and the לוה loveh are agreeing, the loan was
paid off, whatever, that Rav says no, that's way too dangerous. That
is only done under the auspices of בית דין. beis din. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי ברייתא, mai braisa,
where was this ברייתא braisa that made it clear that רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda himself was agreed that you do it from the earlier
date? מאי ברייתא? mai braisa? דתניא, detanya, it's taught in a ברייתא:
braisa: הרי שהיה נושה בו אלף זוז. harei shehaya nosheh bo elef
zuz. So this ברייתא braisa pretty much is just a restatement of
the משנה Mishnah except with greater clarity. First it greater concretizes the
case, and ב bais it makes רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda position clearer.
הרי שהיה נושה בו אלף זוז, harei shehaya nosheh bo elef zuz,
somebody owed a thousand dollars, ופרע לו חמש מאות זוז, u'para lo
chamesh me'os zuz, and he paid up five hundred. עדים מקרעין את
השטר וכותבין לו שטר אחר מזמן ראשון דברי רבי יהודה. eidim mekare'in
es hashtar ve'chosevin lo shtar acher mizman rishon divrei Rebbi Yehuda. The
witnesses tear it up and write a new שטר shtar from the
original date. So this was what we quoted earlier. The ברייתא braisa
makes it clear that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda authorized the רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda said with the original date. And even the עדים eidim
can do it, you don't need it under the auspices of בית
דין. beis din. רבי יוסי אומר שטר זה יונח במקומו. Rebbi Yosi
omer shtar zeh yunach bimkomo. Nope, leave the שטר shtar alone. Okay,
ויכתבו שובר, ve'yichsevu shovar, write a receipt. ומפני שני דברים אמרו כותבין
שובר. u'mipnei shnei devarim amru chosevin shovar. There are two reasons I
say you should write a receipt for the five hundred that was
paid rather than writing a new שטר. shtar. אחת כדי שיכוף לפורעו.
achas kedei she'yachof lepor'o. One is that it creates greater incentive for
the לוה loveh to pay off the rest. Yeah, you're right, it
is dangerous business to have a receipt. You might lose the receipt
and have to pay out the whole thing again. So that because
of he says that doesn't bother me. That actually maybe a good
thing. Provides an incentive to finish paying back the
debt. Okay, יכוף yachof literally means that the מלווה malveh can force
the לוה loveh to pay him, but I'm slightly re-reading it as
because it provides a good incentive to get the לוה loveh to
pay back the rest. Okay, ואחת כדי שיגבה מזמן ראשון. ve'achas kedei
she'yigbeh mizman rishon. And number two is because I want the מלווה
malveh to have his original liens, I want him to have the
right to collect from the earlier date. So there's a little problem,
because רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda already said he agrees to the fact
that it's the earlier date, right? והא רבי יהודה נמי מזמן ראשון
קאמר. ve'ha Rebbi Yehuda nami mizman rishon ka'amar. What what are you
talking about? רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda already himself agreed to the fact
that it's the earlier date. הכי קאמר ליה רבי יוסי לרבי יהודה.
hachi ka'amar lei Rebbi Yosi le'Rebbi Yehuda. Here's what he's saying. Meaning,
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda just said you rewrite
a שטר. shtar. He didn't say the earlier date. Although the ברייתא
braisa quoted him as saying the earlier date, תוספות Tosfos points out
that was really a later gloss of the ברייתא braisa in the
original statement of רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. But רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda
original statement like in our משנה Mishnah doesn't clarify whether it's the
earlier date or not the earlier date. He just said you rewrite
a שטר. shtar. So רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi responds in the following
way: הכי קאמר ליה רבי יוסי לרבי יהודה אי מזמן ראשון אמרת.
hachi ka'amar lei Rebbi Yosi le'Rebbi Yehuda im mizman rishon amart. I
don't know what you mean when you say you rewrite a שטר.
shtar. If you mean to do it from the earlier date, פגמנא
לך בחדא. pagamna lach bechada. Then at least I have one one
critique, which is that I'd rather there be a שובר shovar to
create an incentive to the לוה. loveh. But at least we're not
hurting the interests of the מלווה. malveh. But אי מזמן שני אמרת,
im mizman sheni amarta, if what you mean is... says he write
a new שטר shtar from the current date, then פלגינן עלך בתרתי,
palginan alach betarti, then I have two critiques. Number one is I
want to create an incentive for the לוה, loveh, but number two
is you're hurting the interests of the מלוה. malveh. So this is
very interesting, right, because now we understand why Reb Yose in the
משנה Mishnah said I'd rather write a receipt than hurt the interests
of the מלוה, malveh, because Reb Yose understood Reb Yehuda like Rav
did to mean the earlier date. But the author of the b—I
mean excuse me, to mean the later date. That's what that—that's what
it sounded like Reb Yehuda was saying. But the author of the
ברייתא Braita came along and clarified both for Reb Yose's sake and
for Rav's sake: No, no, no, don't worry, Reb Yehuda also says
it means the original date. Okay? So the ברייתא Braita clarified it.
But the original statement of Reb Yehuda was not clear, which is
why Reb Yose responded as he did. Okay, take a look at
the little תוספות Tosafot מזמן ראשון. mizman rishon. רבי יהודה לא פירש
לרבי יוסי Reb Yehuda lo peireish leReb Yose מזמן ראשון. mizman rishon.
Reb Yehuda just said you rewrite a שטר. shtar. Okay, and that's
why Reb Yose thought and Rav thought he meant from the second
date. Okay, אבל ברייתא aval Braita פישנויה במילתיה דרבי יהודה לפי האמת.
pishnuyeh bemiltei deReb Yehuda lefi ha'emet. The ברייתא Braita went and added
it to Reb Yehuda's words to clarify Reb Yehuda's position. But Reb
Yose—it's interesting, like the later author of the ברייתא Braita who recapped
the debate, you know, either because he heard Reb Yehuda had responded
to Reb Yose this way or he just felt it was such
a good critique, the only reasonable way to explain Reb Yehuda was
to say he meant from the earlier date. But that was something
that was added later to clarify Reb Yehuda. Okay, but that explains
why Reb Yose is saying you're going to hurt the interests of
the מלוה malveh and why Rav thought that he had to introduce
the idea of the בית דין Beis Din because that wasn't clear
in the statement of Reb Yehuda. Okay.
Rav mentions בית דין Beis Din also.
Right, so what the גמרא Gemara then does is, is that it
says no, no, no, no, no, even with the ברייתא, Braita, Rav
was introducing the idea of בית דין. Beis Din. Correct. So that's
what the גמרא's Gemara response was, that even with knowing the ברייתא,
Braita, Rav's statement was still important to introduce the requirement of בית
דין. Beis Din. Okay, but at a certain level, the bigger issue
going on here
or leading with that—Exactly, right, exactly.
Reb Yehuda and Reb Yehuda allows it to be even עדים, eidim,
that is correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Okay, תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שטר שזמנו כתוב בשבת או בעשרה
בתשרי, sh'tar shezmano katuv beShabbos o be'asarah beTishrei, a שטר shtar says
on שבת Shabbos so-and-so borrowed $1,000 and we signed it. Okay, or
it says on the 10th of תשרי. Tishrei. Now the way sort
of it's going to be clear in the גמרא, Gemara, but I'll
just sort of say now is, it maybe doesn't say it so
blatantly. What it says is on the 13th of the month so-and-so
borrowed $100, and you looked up at your calendar and you said,
wait, that's a שבת. Shabbos. Okay, or it says like on the
second
Sunday—on the second Monday of תשרי, Tishrei, and you say wait, second
Monday of תשרי? Tishrei? That was יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so
it doesn't maybe explicitly say it, but it's—that's what it is. It
winds up being שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay. שטר
מאוחר הוא וכשר דברי רבי יהודה. Shtar me'uchar hu vekasher divrei Reb
Yehuda. Reb Yehuda says not a problem, you're allowed to postdate a
שטר, shtar, so we'll just assume it's postdated. Now it could be
predated, okay, but the point is this goes to the fact that
somebody holding onto a שטר shtar with witnesses is that the same
way we say, you know, עדים החתומים על השטר נעשה כמי שנחקרו
עדותן בבית דין, eidim hachatumim al hash'tar na'aseh kemi shenechkeru edutan beveis
din, that מן התורה min haTorah they don't even need to be
validated, the signatures. The power of a שטר shtar is that if
you're holding onto it,
there's a presumption that it's understood
to be giving a valid testimony. So since the only way for
this to be a valid testimony is to interpret it to be
a postdated שטר, shtar, we're going to interpret it as a postdated
שטר shtar rather than as a predated שטר. shtar. Okay, so that's
what Reb Yehuda says and therefore it's going to be כשר. kasher.
רבי יוסי פוסל. Reb Yose posel. Reb Yose invalidates. So it seems
that Reb Yose not just invalidates it because it was written on
שבת Shabbos and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, actually it's going to be
a little bit ironic the opposite. He invalidates a standard postdated שטר.
shtar. One minute. אמר לו רבי יהודה לרבי יוסי, Amar lo Reb
Yehuda leReb Yose, so Reb Yehuda said to Reb Yose: והלא מעשה
בא לפניך בציפורי, Vehalo ma'aseh ba lifanecha beTzippori, what do you mean,
a case like this came in front of you in ציפורי Tzippori
והכשרת vehichsharta and you yourself said such a שטר shtar was good.
אמר לו כשהכשרתי, Amar lo keshehichsharti, when I validated such a שטר,
shtar, בזה הכשרתי, bezeh hichsharti, it was like the case you were
talking about, that it's dated on שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Okay, so what does that mean? It means the way at
least the גמרא's Gemara going to explain and this is a little
ironic because it didn't sound this way initially, that he says actually
if the שטר shtar is clear that it's postdated or that it's
wrongly dated, I'm more prepared to say it's okay. So yes, when
I said a שטר shtar was okay, it was when you checked
up the dates and you saw it was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you saw it was שבת. Shabbos. Then it's evident that it was
a postdated שטר. shtar. What I'm concerned about is a שטר shtar
that's postdated that there's no evidence that it's postdated. That could be
abused. Now we're going to see in a minute how it could
be abused, but ironically and it didn't sound this way, it sounded
like he was פוסל pasuling it because it couldn't be written on
שבת. Shabbos. But that's not how we're going to interpret what he's
saying. What he's saying is פסול pasul if it's postdated and not
clear that it's postdated. And when I כשר kashered a postdated שטר
shtar was when it was clear it was postdated because it was
שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Charlie, you had a question.
We are assuming that the folks involved were not
מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. If the מלווה malveh is
okay with it, fine, sure. Okay, so now let's take understand what
this debate is about. אמר רבי פדת, Amar Rabi Padas, הכל מודים
היכא דדקקו לאונתו של שטר, hakol modim haycha d'dikdeku l'onaso shel shtar,
ונמצא אונתו מכוונת בשבת או בעשרה בתשרי, venimtza onaso mechuvents b'Shabbos o
b'asara b'Tishrei, ששטר מאוחר וכשר. she'shtar me'uchar v'kasher.
So he's going to clarify what I just said, which is he
says everybody agrees that if you have to check up the date
and you find that it was שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, meaning it's clear from the שטר shtar that it was שבת
Shabbos or יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, like we're talking about, okay, then
it's clear that it's a שטר מאוחר shtar me'uchar and then it's
כשר. kasher. Okay.
Now, לא נחלקו, lo nechelku, so then what is the debate? So
ironically the debate is not about the יום כיפור Yom Kippur or
the שבת Shabbos שטר. shtar. That's fine. The debate is about a
normal postdated שטר. shtar. לא נחלקו אלא בשטר מאוחר בעלמא, lo nechelku
ela b'shtar me'uchar b'alma, standard postdated שטר. shtar. דרבי יהודה לטעמיה. de'Rabi
Yehuda l'taameih. So now why would רבי יהודה, Rabi Yehuda, so let's
get it straight, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says that a postdated שטר
shtar is כשר. kasher. רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאמר אין כותבין שובר. Rabi
Yehuda l'taameih d'amar ein kotvin shovar. So remember, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda
doesn't like receipts. Okay, so what happens when you pay up a
loan? You either rewrite the שטר shtar or you get the שטר
shtar back and you tear it up. ולא נפקא מיניה חורבא, v'lo
nafka minei churva, so there's no danger, there's nothing bad that can
happen with a postdated שטר. shtar. All right, why is that not
true for רבי יוסי? Rabi Yosi? Let's take a look. ורבי יוסי
לטעמיה דאמר כותבין שובר. v'Rabi Yosi l'taameih d'amar kotvin shovar. You write
a receipt. ונפקא מיניה חורבא. v'nafka minei churva. Something really bad could
happen. What could happen? Michael, I borrow... I borrow a thousand dollars
from Michael today. Okay, what's today? י"ז בתמוז. Yud Zayin b'Tammuz. So
we're going to say I borrow, I'm not supposed to, it's bad
to borrow money during the three weeks
there. Okay, then, put myself in a bad position to Michael. Anyway,
but we're going to postdate it and we're going to say that
I borrowed it from him for on ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh
Elul. Okay, so now before ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, so
the שטר shtar said I borrowed him a thousand dollars on ראש
חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. Before the שטר shtar of אלול Elul
is out, I have the money. Michael, here's your thousand dollars back.
It's now תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. I want to get you off
my back on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, here's the thousand dollars back.
So Michael says, give me my שטר. shtar. Michael says, oh, terrible
thing, I lost the שטר. shtar. But don't worry, I'll write you
a שובר. shovar. Dov paid me back a thousand dollars on תשעה
באב. Tisha B'Av.
Signed, signed Michael Katzman. Okay, comes along ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh
Elul and Michael takes up the שטר shtar that was dated ראש
חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul and says where's my thousand dollars? So
what are you talking about? I paid you off. He said no,
that was a different loan. You just borrowed a thousand dollars from
me today. Okay, so if you postdate a שטר shtar and you
write a שובר, shovar, then you could wind up paying the... the
debt that's in the שטר, shtar, but the person will claim that
that was some other debt. And this money was lent later. What?
You could postdate the שובר. shovar. So I could demand that you
postdate the שובר, shovar, but maybe I'm not going to be so
on my... on my toes to remember that.
Okay, so how do we explain היכא דדקקו לאונתו של שטר? haycha
d'dikdeku l'onaso shel shtar? What? How do we explain that exactly? נפקא
מיניה חורבא? nafka minei churva? The team who's before, היכא דדקקו לאונתו
של שטר. haycha d'dikdeku l'onaso shel shtar.
If we had to check the dates, if we checked the dates
and we realized that it was a שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור
Yom Kippur שכתבו... she'kasvu... when, no, the date that was put on
it. It said... it said the second Monday of תשרי Tishrei and
we looked up on a calendar we realized that was יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Or it said the thirteenth of תשרי Tishrei and we
looked up on a calendar we saw that it was a שבת.
Shabbos. All right. So... okay, so because of יוסי Yosi says you
write a שובר, shovar, he says I'm... I'm going to invalidate a
postdated שטר shtar because the person will pay up, get a שובר,
shovar, and it'll look like from the שטר shtar that there was
a new loan, a loan that after the debt after the other
debt that was paid up. Okay, and therefore I'm going to have
to invalidate a postdated שטר. shtar.
But רבי יהודה's Rabi Yehuda not a problem, you'll tear up the
שטר. shtar. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, אפילו למאן דאמר כותבין שובר, afilu l'man d'amar kotvin shovar,
even if you say you can write a שובר, shovar, הני מילי
אפלגא. hani mili apalga. You would only write a שובר shovar for...
if the person was partial payment, because otherwise we would agree that
you would have to pay up the whole... you would have to
give back the שטר shtar and tear up the whole שטר. shtar.
Okay, אבל אכולא לא. aval akula lo.
But on the whole value, no. The whole value, we could demand,
I'm not going to give you your thousand dollars until you give
me my שטר. shtar. You said you lost your שטר, shtar, tough
luck, I'm not going to give you your money until you give
me my שטר. shtar. Okay, so what happens then?
He really lost it.
So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. Okay, ולא היא.
v'lo hi. That's not true. אפילו אכולא כתבינן. afilu akula kasvinan. We
would even write a שובר shovar on the full amount. The guy
could legitimately have lost the שטר shtar and he's entitled to write
a receipt. Okay, for the full amount.
כי הא דרב יצחק בר יוסף ki ha d'Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef
הוי מסיק ביה זוזי ברבי אבא. hava masik bei zuzei b'Rabi Abba.
He lent money to רבי אבא. Rabi Abba. אתא לקמיה דרבי חנינא
בר פפא. asa l'kamei d'Rabi Chanina bar Pappa. The case came to
רבי חנינא בר פפא. Rabi Chanina bar Pappa. אמר ליה הב לי
זוזי. amar lei hav li zuzei. So... so רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak
said to... to who was it? To רבי אבא, Rabi Abba, give
me my money. So אמר ליה הב לי שטראי, amar lei hav
li shtarai, give me my שטר, shtar, ושקול זוזך, ushkol zuzach, and
I'll give you your money when you give me back the שטר.
shtar. so I can tear it up. אמר ליה שטרא אירכס לי.
Amar lei shtara irkas li. I lost your שטר. shtar. אכתוב לך
תברא. Evtov lach tavra. I'll write you a receipt. אמר ליה הא
רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו אין כותבין שובר. Amar lei ha Rav ve
Shmuel d amrei duvayhu ein kotvin shovra. No, רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel say they both פוסקים passken like whoever, I guess like רבי
יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, and they say we don't write שוברים shovas and
therefore since we don't write שוברים shovas and I have to have
the responsibility of holding onto a receipt, then if you don't give
me back my שטר, shtar, I'm going to be, I'm not going
to pay you. So okay, wait a minute, so this is the
approach that you don't write a שובר. shova. But then, but, but
אמר מאן יהיב לן מעפריה דרב ושמואל ורמינן בעינין. amar man yeiv
lan me-afrei de-Rav u-Shmuel ve-raminan be-einin. Who would give us from the
dust of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel we would put it in
our eyes. Okay, it's an interesting expression, but meaning like you know,
I admit I'm nothing in the presence of רב Rav and שמואל,
Shmuel, like you know, I should only merit to eat their dust
or something, to have their dust in my eyes. But it also
sort of means that what they teach might blind us to other
opinions. Okay, so because even though they say that, הא רבי יוחנן
והא ריש לקיש. ha Rebbi Yochanan ve-ha Reish Lakish. There's רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Okay,
these good two ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמוראים Amoraim דאמרי תרוייהו d'amrei
duvayhu they both say כותבין שובר, kotvin shovra, you write a שובר.
shova. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי אלעא כותבין שובר. ve-chen ki
ata Ravin amar Rebbi Ela'a kotvin shovra. So it seems now there
might be a little בבל Bavel ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מחלוקת. machlokes.
You write a שובר. shova. Now, and here the שובר shova is
for the full amount. So that's why the גמרא Gemara is saying
you see from this story that according to those who say you
write a שובר, shova, you even can write it for the full
amount. Okay, but you understand when it's a partial amount you could
say there's a reason to write a, a real pressure to write
a שובר shova because we don't like rewriting the old שטר. shtar.
But the full amount you could say no, now it's just give
back the old שטר shtar or nothing. But no, the גמרא Gemara
rejects that and says the גמרא Gemara says you write a שובר,
shova, says you can write it even for the full amount if
the person can't find the שטר. shtar. Dov, you had a question?
Yeah, this is not conceptual. Yesterday I think we had the expression
like if it's no good, it's just like חספא בעלמא, chaspa be-alma,
it's like pottery.
That suggested to me that all of these receipts were written on
pottery, not papyrus.
No, because pottery can be forged, so it's actually, but
is it possible that maybe all of these?
No, I think it's the opposite. Pottery means that it's not a
שטר, shtar, not because it wasn't written on pottery. Pottery was forgeable.
Yeah.
Meaning
you could erase I think if I'm remembering correctly from the גמרא
Gemara in גיטין, Gittin, you could erase the stuff on the top
and you'd have the signatures on the bottom and you couldn't see
that it was erased. Pretty sure that the גמרא Gemara in גיטין
Gittin makes it clear that that pottery was דווקא davka not כשר
kosher because it was ראוי לזיוף ra'uy le-ziyuf if I'm remembering correctly.
Okay, so there was some issue of reality of writing on pottery
and then they had to say no, these types of documents cannot
be.
Right. From what I remember that is correct, yes. Okay,
what?
It's correct.
You can scrape off the
thing from the pottery and not see. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Same thing with cloth.
No, but the גמרא Gemara claims that then you could see that
it's been scraped. Yeah, okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
okay, so now that we have now this debate between ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and בבל, Bavel, essentially it's the debate of רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi. Do we פוסקים passken you
write a שובר shova or you have to give back the שטר?
shtar? And we see that those that say you that that it's
even for the full amount you those that say you write a
שובר shova would say even for the full amount you write a
שובר. shova. We do not demand that you give back the שטר.
shtar. Okay. ומסתברא u-mistabra and now he said in going back to
this case that the רבי חנינא Rebbi Chanina had to adjudicate that
there wasn't a שטר shtar to give back. So we've got this
debate of and what how did he פוסקים? passken? דכותבין שובר. de-kotvin
shovra. No, we write a שובר. shova. Give him his money, he'll
write you a receipt. It's too bad he doesn't have the שטר
shtar but he'll write you a receipt. דאי סלקא דעתך אין כותבין
שובר. de-i salka dach-tach ein kotvin shovra. Here's the question might go
with asking or everybody should ask. Because if you won't write if
you say that you you don't write a
receipt, so אבד שטרו של זה יאכל הלה ויחדי? avad shtaro shel
zeh yochel haleh ve-yechadi? So because this person's שטר shtar got lost,
the לווה loveh should sort of consume the person's money and rejoice?
You lent me a thousand dollars, ha ha, I don't have to
pay you, you lost your שטר. shtar. So clearly that is not
fair to the מלווה. malveh. Okay, and therefore you have to we
if the מלווה malveh says he lost the שטר, shtar, yes, you
have to go ahead and write yes, the לווה loveh have to
accept a receipt. Okay. Where's the expression? This one should go and
rejoice, should eat and rejoice? יאכל ויחדי?
yochel
ve-yechadi?
Yeah, exactly. So מתקיף לה אביי. matkif lah Abaye. So אביי Abaye
asks back. ואלא מאי כותבין שובר? ve-ela mai kotvin shovra? So what
do you want to say? Let's protect the interests of the מלווה
malveh and say that he writes a receipt. So that's true, אבד
שוברו של זה יאכל הלה ויחדי? avad shovro shel zeh yochel haleh
ve-yechadi? So
let's say the לווה loveh loses his receipt. So now the מלווה
malveh should go and rejoice and the מלווה malveh should be able
to collect twice? Okay, so that's not going to be fair now
to the לווה. loveh. Now that only assumes that the מלווה malveh
is lying, right? If the מלווה malveh is being honest and and
that he lost his שטר, shtar, then even if the לווה loveh
loses his receipt, the מלווה malveh doesn't have any, right, the מלווה
malveh no longer has his proof that money is owed. So the
concern here that it would be unfair is only assuming
that the מלווה malveh is lying, okay? Whereas you understand there's a
big difference. In the first case, I admit I owe you $1,000
but I'm not paying you until I get my שטר, shtar, okay?
So that's really like that's totally unfair. I'm admitting I owe you
the money, haha, I'm not paying. In the other case, don't give
him a receipt, maybe he'll lose the receipt and maybe this guy
is lying and we'll pull out his שטר shtar and collect this
loan twice. So that concern requires the possibility that the guy is
lying, okay? But nevertheless, says the גמרא, Gemara, there's a concern that
way as well. If you write a שובר shovar that might give
an opening for the מלווה malveh to collect twice. דילמא כתבינן שובר
דאכיל לווה וחדא? Dilma katvinan shovar d'achil loveh v'chada? Or are you
going to allow the מלווה malveh to collect twice? אמר ליה רבא
אין, Amar lei Rava in, yes! If we have to take a
risk, we'll take a risk on the side of the לווה, loveh,
not on the side of the מלווה. malveh. Why? עבד לווה לאיש
מלווה. Eved loveh l'ish malveh. Because the לווה loveh is a slave
to the מלווה. malveh. Now to some degree that could be seen
as something that is problematic and needs to be critiqued, right? All
of the protections in the תורה, Torah, לא תהיה לו כנשה, lo
tihyeh lo k'nosheh, you know, don't go ahead and go into his
home and take collateral, you know, and it's you know don't go
ahead and act like a like a creditor, you know, sort of
exact payment from him, all of that is to try to protect
the לווה loveh from that power dynamic, that imbalanced power that the
מלווה malveh has over him, right? So you could see a lot
of the מצוות mitzvot of the תורה Torah that are trying to
actually somewhat ameliorate that situation. Okay, but nevertheless here the גמרא's Gemara
actually saying but there's a truth to it. He lent you money,
you're indebted to him, especially in the according to הלכה halacha where
he's not getting interest and didn't get anything out of it, okay,
yes, you are indebted to him. And therefore that means that he
should be the one to or assume more of the responsibility here
than he should.
Okay, so he right now he's out his money, he doesn't have
his money paid back. Okay, so therefore and that to some degree
this could be a restatement of the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. Who should bear the burden of
the responsibility? Should it be the לווה loveh or the מלווה? malveh?
And here the גמרא's Gemara saying is yeah, write a if now
ideally, give back the שטר shtar and tear it up. But if
you can't give back the שטר shtar and tear it up, we're
not going to ask the מלווה malveh to lose out the money
he gave. It's going to be the לווה's loveh responsibility to watch
his שובר, shovar, yes.
Right, but wait, but this says עבד לווה לאיש מלווה Eved loveh
l'ish malveh is saying though that it's the מלווה's malveh responsibility?
No, the לווה's loveh the slave to the מלווה. malveh. So the
לווה's loveh the one who has greater responsibility. He has the burden
of responsibility. Why should we make the מלווה malveh the one that
has to or that has to, you know, be the one that
assumes the risk?
I see the point, okay.
Do you think that it's an interesting formulation that עבד eved and
איש ish are juxtaposed?
Oh, that one is like a slave and the other is a
man. That's a good point, rather than just עבד לווה למלווה. eved
loveh l'malveh. I mean, it's partly to create a balance of the
words in the פסוקים, pesukim, but you're right, that's a very interesting
contrast. Yeah, it's a very good point. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Okay,
now we're going to continue to discuss this issue about a about
a post-dated שטר shtar and about the writing of a receipt because
now we said that if you allow receipts, you shouldn't allow a
post-dated שטר shtar because it's open for abuse. Okay, now we're going
to see if that's really true or if that really if we
really פסקן pasken that you can't have both. תנן התם, Tnan hatam,
we taught over there in שביעית. Shevi'it. שטרי חוב המוקדמין פסולין והמאוחרים
כשרין. Shtarei chov hamukdamin psulin v'hameucharim ksherin.
Pre-dated שטרות shtarot are invalid because they create early liens, post-dated שטרות
shtarot are valid because they just mean that you're forfeiting your liens
for a certain period of time. Okay, which seems to be consistent
with the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position that allows post-dated שטרות. shtarot.
אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna, לא שנו אלא שטרי חוב, lo
shanu ela shtarei chov, that's only loan documents. אבל שטרי מקח וממכר,
Aval shtarei mekach u'mimkar, but purchase documents, אפילו מאוחרים נמי פסולים afilu
meucharim nami psulim
are also invalid. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? זימנין דמזבין ליה ארעא
בניסן, Zimnin d'mazbin lei ar'ah b'Nissan,
so I go ahead and I'm buying this land from Charlie in
Nissan. וכתב ליה בתשרי, V'katav lei b'Tishrei, and we post-dated to Tishrei.
Now, what happens between Nissan and Tishrei? ומשלמי ליה זוזי ביני ביני.
U'mashlami lei zuzei beini beini.
Now, now in the interim, Charlie gets money to buy the land
back, because most of the time people sold land not because they
were making money but because they need money, right? They were hard
up. So Charlie sells me this land. We post-date it. Okay. In
the interim, he gets he raises some cash
and he wants to buy it back from me and I'm a
nice guy and I'm willing to sell it back to him, okay?
The רשב"ם Rashbam even imagines that maybe we even made a clause
or an agreement in the sale that I would sell it back
to him if he were to be able to raise the funds
within a certain amount of time. Okay, so Charlie raises the funds
and buys it back. וזבין ליה מיניה, V'zabin lei minei, so very
nice. וכי מטי תשרי, V'chi mati Tishrei, now Tishrei rolls about, מפיק
ליה, mapik lei, I take out this שטר shtar that says that
I bought it from him. you in תשרי Tishrei cause we postdated
it. Okay? ואמר ליה, V'amar lei, הדר זבנתי מינך. hadar zavinti minach.
Yes, you bought it back from me and then I bought it
back from you and that's a second time. And here's the שטר
shtar that says that I bought it in תשרי. Tishrei. So you
don't postdate a purchase document because that will be given to abuse
that you might the guy might resell back to the owner and
then claim you bought it back afterwards. Okay?
So that's why you can't postdate that. So the גמרא Gemara says
אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, שטרי הלואה נמי, Shtarei halvaa
nami,
a loan document as well, זימנין דיזיף בניסן, zimnin d'yazif b'Nissan, let's
say I borrow a thousand dollars from Charlie in
ניסן, Nissan, וכתבי ליה שטרא בתשרי, v'chtavi lei shtar b'Tishrei, but we
write that I borrowed it in תשרי. Tishrei. I'm sorry, actually let's
say Charlie borrowed the money from me. Okay, so it's the same
sort of roles. Charlie borrows a thousand dollars from me and we
say that he borrowed it in תשרי, Tishrei, six months from now.
ומיסרמי ליה זוזי ביני וביני, u'misrami lei zuzei b'nei u'v'nei, and in
the interim Charlie gets the money to pay me back, ופרע ליה,
u'fara lei, and pays me back. ואמר ליה, v'amar lei, הב לי
שטראי, hav li shtarai, and he says give me my שטר. shtar.
ואמר ליה, v'amar lei, אירכס לי, irkas li, I lost it. So
this is exactly rehashing what we said before. Okay, that if you
post, if you allow for receipts and you postdate a שטר, shtar,
I can collect twice. Oh, Charlie, bad news, I lost the שטר.
shtar. וכתבי ליה שובר, v'chtavi lei shovar, don't worry, here's a receipt
dated as of today. וכי מטי זמניה, v'chi mati zmanei, then when
תשרי Tishrei rolls around, מפיק ליה, mapik lei, I take out the
שטר, shtar, ואמר ליה, v'amar lei, הא השתא הוא דיזפת מינאי, ha
hashta hu d'yazfat minai, you just lent you money again here in
תשרי. Tishrei. Charlie, you're always borrowing money from me. You borrowed it
six months ago, now you borrowed it again in תשרי, Tishrei, so
I claim that he borrowed it just now and I'm going to
collect a second time. So if you're worried that the person will
retake the land and claim he bought it a second time, why
aren't you concerned with a postdated שטר shtar that he'll claim he
lent money a second time and collect twice? Okay? קסבר אין כותבין
שובר. Kasavar ein kotvin shovar. Oh,
that's not a problem, because you don't write receipts. So I won't,
no, no, but this would be the position that you don't. Postdated
documents, the problem is, you know, can you both allow postdated documents
and writing receipts? We're going to get to that, but right now
we're saying they don't go together. Okay? So if you allow a
postdated שטר, shtar, you won't allow a receipt. So therefore, when I
Charlie when Charlie comes to pay me up, I can't say I
lost my שטר. shtar. Charlie won't give me the money until I
give him back the שטר. shtar. Okay, and therefore if I'm going
to give back the שטר shtar and he's going to tear it
up, there's no risk about a postdated שטר. shtar. But the same
doesn't work for a sale document. Why? Because if Charlie buys that
land back from me, he doesn't have a right to ask for
the original deed. What happens if Charlie buys the land back from
me two months from now? What does he ask from me?
I bought the land from Charlie two months ago, he wrote out
a deed to me, two months from now he buys back that
land. Does he say give me back the deed so I can
tear it up? No. What do you say when you buy land?
What are you entitled to ask for when I'm buying land from
somebody? Title to. Give me a deed right now, write a deed
right now in my name. That's not a שובר. shovar. Fine, I'll
write a deed in your name. And then four months from now,
I'll take out my postdated deed. Okay, so שובר shovar we can
say that Charlie can say I don't accept a receipt, if you
want me to pay my debt, give me back the original שטר.
shtar. So I give back the original שטר, shtar, he tears it
up, he's protected. But when he comes to, but that's why you
can never postdate a loan document. But a postdated purchase document, if
Charlie buys it back from me, he's not in a position to
demand the original document. He's only in a position to demand a
title now, and I'm still holding on to the original postdated one.
Right, exactly. So we won't allow a postdated sale document because you
because the guy could hold on to it and pull it out.
We will allow a postdated loan document because the guy could hold
on to, because the guy can't hold on to it, because we
won't let the guy write a receipt and Charlie won't have to
pay up his loan until I can give him the original document.
So because he can demand the original document, we allow it to
be postdated. Okay, so once again we're saying if you like if
you want to allow postdated documents, you will not allow receipts. You
will only have to pay if you can get the original document
back. But that's not going to be where we're going to end
up.
So let's keep on going. Okay.
אמר ליה רב יימר לרב כהנא. Amar lei Rav Yeimar l'Rav Kahana.
So Rav Yeimar said to Rav Kahana. ואמרי לה רב ירמיה מדיפתי
לרב כהנא. V'amrei lah Rav Yirmiyah mi-Difti l'Rav Kahana. והאידנא דכתבינן שטרי
מאוחרי, V'haidna d'chtavinan shtarei meucharim,
but that doesn't work with the way we practice right now, because
right now we write postdated documents וכתבינן שובר, v'chtavinan shovar, and we
write receipts. So we've got the problem, it's open to abuse. What
are you going to do? אמאי עבדינן הכי, Amai avdinan hachi, we
read with the parentheses, why do we do this? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, בתר דאמר להו רב אבא לספריה, basar d'amar lehu Rav Abba
l'safrei, no, because here's what Rav Abba has instructed his scribes in
order to allow postdated and receipts. Here's what he says to his
scribes: כי כתביתו שטרי מאוחרי, Ki chtavitu shtarei meucharim, when you write
a postdated document, כתבו הכי, kitvu hachi, write the following: שטרא דנן
לאו בזמניה כתבנוהו, Shtara dnan lav b'zmanei chtavnu-hu,
this שטר shtar was not written on the date that it appeared,
אלא איחרנוהו וכתבנוהו, ela icharnuhu u'chtavnu-hu, we postdated it. Now, by the
way, I forgot to mention that earlier, that's why רב Rav Remember
even רב יוסי Reb Yose allowed for a post-dated document when it
was שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור Yom Kippur because it was clear
it was post-dated. Why does it work if it’s clear it’s post-dated?
Because what’s going to happen?
Charlie’s going to give me the thousand dollars, I say, oh I
lost my שטר, shtar, רבותי, rabbosai, here’s a receipt. Okay, then six
months from now I take it out and I say, look, here
you owe me a thousand dollars. It says that I borrowed it
today. So Charlie's going to say, no it doesn't, it says explicitly
it was post-dated. Or it says it was שבת Shabbos or יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, so obviously it was post-dated. Okay, and since it
was post-dated, here's the interesting thing. I'll say, fine, it was post-dated,
but maybe it was still after I lent you that original money,
right? But no, once it's clear it was post-dated and once he's
got a receipt that he says he paid a thousand dollar שטר,
shtar, and he has a thousand dollar שטר shtar that's clear it's
post-dated, then we're going to assume that that receipt is going on
this שטר. shtar.
What if he doesn't have a receipt but it's clear it was
post-dated?
Well that's the שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור Yom Kippur case. That's
also, no he doesn't have a receipt? No, that doesn't matter. I
have a שטר. shtar. It doesn't do anything. I have a
שטר. shtar. It's clearly post-dated is כשר, kosher, right? So this is
what we said before, right? That every שטר shtar you need a
שובר shovar against it, but here even רב יהודה Reb Yehuda who
allows, even רב יוסי Reb Yose who allows for receipts will allow
it if it's clear it's post-dated. You either say explicitly this is
a post-dated document or it's שבת Shabbos or יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
and that way the fact that this says a thousand dollars and
Charlie has a receipt from six months ago of a thousand dollars,
we're going to assume that it's the same שטר. shtar. Now the
רשב"ם Rashbam says, I've got to be really careful. You know why?
Because that means now for the rest of my life,
okay, I can never write a post-dated שטר shtar for Charlie
that's clearly post-dated for the same amount of an earlier debt I
lent him. If once, ten years ago, I lent Charlie a thousand
dollars and gave him a receipt, I better not write for him
a post-dated שטר shtar that says it's post-dated for a thousand dollars
because then he'll always claim that that receipt is going on this
שטר. shtar. So either I have to not post-date any שטרות shtarot
for Charlie, okay, or I've got to make sure it's a thousand
dollars and a penny, or something like that, yeah.
Now what if you have it clearly post-dated, you don't have a
שובר shovar but you have two witnesses?
The two witnesses
that it was paid off? Yeah, that's fine. Sure, you don't need
a שובר shovar if you have witnesses. Okay, so now but we're
not done. אמליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, Amley Rav Ashi L'Rav Kahana,
ואידנא דלא כבדינן הכי, ve-idna d'lo kavdinan hachi, so for one minute,
but nowadays we don't even do that. We don't even explicitly write
in the שטר shtar that it was post-dated. We post-date it without
saying that it was post-dated.
Okay, דאמליה רב ספרא לספריה, D'Amley Rav Safra L'Safrei, because רב ספרא
Rav Safra now says to his scribes, כי כתביתו הני תברי, ki
kasevitu hani tavrei, when you write a receipt,
אי ידעיתו זמנא דשטרא כתבו, i-yaditu zimna d'shtara kisvu, if you know
the date of the שטר shtar write it. So this is what
sort of, if we know that שטר shtar was dated
as of תשרי Tishrei and it's now ניסן, Nissan, so when Charlie
pays me off, say he paid me on תשרי. Tishrei. I've got
a שטר shtar dated as תשרי, Tishrei, say he paid me on
תשרי. Tishrei. If you know that the שטר shtar is post-dated, just
post-date the receipt. Okay, so that'll solve that problem.
ואילו כתבו סתמא. v'ilo kisvu stama. But and if not, if you
don't know when the שטר shtar was dated, here's how you're going
to solve the problem of me reusing the שטר shtar of a
post-dated שטר. shtar. Write an undated receipt for Charlie. Oh, so then
he can, don't date Charlie's receipt. So if I come six months
from now and say, oh look you just borrowed money from me
because it was post-dated for six months from now, Charlie will take
out his undated receipt and say yeah and I just paid you
up. Okay, so an undated receipt is actually a very dangerous, it's
like a blank check. If somebody gives Charlie an undated receipt, okay,
then which now will be the standard, so the standard is when
Charlie pays me up we don't know for certain when the שטר
shtar was dated. So now
we're giving the לוה, loveh, on the one hand if he loses
his receipt he's out, on the other hand he's got some dangerous
weapon here. If I ever lend him the same amount of money,
he can always come out with his undated receipt and say he
just paid me up. And this is actually even more dangerous because
let's say the original loan was a thousand dollars and the בית
דין beis din didn't know the date and they thought maybe it
was a post-dated document, so they wrote him a receipt for a
thousand dollars undated. So let's say a year from now I lent
him ten thousand dollars and I come back and I say where's
my ten thousand? And he says I only owe you nine thousand,
here's this undated receipt that I've already paid you a thousand. Right,
so it's very tricky. Maybe the receipt says paid in full a
thousand, you know. So then but and then that makes it, limits
the abuse. But I still have to be careful to never lend
Charlie a thousand dollars again because he's got an undated receipt that
says paid in full a thousand dollars. Okay, so
but here's how we're going to solve the problem. of a שטר
מאוחר shtar me'uchar is we're going to give to the person an
undated receipt. אלא כי סתמא, ilo kis stama, דכל אימת דנפיק, d'chol
eimas d'nafik, anytime he takes it out ליראי lirei he could he
he will anytime I take out my post-dated שטר, shtar, Charlie can
undermine it because of his non-dated receipt. But again, as the Rashbam
says, I better not lend him the same amount of money. Okay,
I assume as I said, the receipt would say paid in full,
so I could lend him more money, but I better not lend
him that exact amount of money because then he'll just take out
his undated receipt. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina l'Rav
Ashi, so one last line. So Ravina said to Rav Ashi, ואמרי
לה רב אשי לרב כהנא, v'amri lah Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana, or
Rav Ashi said to Rav Kahana, והאידנא דלא כתבינן הכי, v'ha'idna d'lo
kasbinan hachi, but now we don't do that, we write a post-dated
שטר shtar and a dated receipt. So where it's given to abuse,
right? You got how it's given to abuse? We're back to that
thing. It's a post-dated שטר, shtar, I'm holding onto a post-dated שטר,
shtar, I give Charlie a dated receipt, and then six months from
now, I'm going to say, here's a new loan, pay me up.
Okay? So what do you do? How do you explain the practice
right now? אמר ליה, amar lei, רבנן תקוני תקוני. Rabanan takuni takuni.
The rabbis fixed the problem or they made, they established the procedures.
They told you that if you're going to have a post-dated שטר,
shtar, either explicitly write in it that it's post-dated or give people
undated receipts. We set it up so that the system can work,
okay? מאן דעביד עביד, man d'avid avid, if you follow our rules,
good. מאן דלא עביד, man d'lo avid, if you're not going to
follow our rules, איהו דאפסיד אנפשיה, ihu d'afsid anafshei, then you're just
hurting yourself. So Charlie here, who is paying me up and there
was a post-dated שטר, shtar, Charlie has got to protect his interests.
And Charlie has to know that either when he borrows the money
and we post-date it, the סופר sofer explicitly writes in the שטר
shtar that it's post-dated, or when he gets a receipt from me,
he demands that it be an undated receipt. And if he doesn't
know that and I'm willing and I'm able to get a post-dated
שטר shtar and a dated receipt, then Charlie is like, you know,
tough luck Charlie. We made the rules, if you would have listened
or asked, you would have known what to do and now you
don't and now, yes, it is possible to be abused. Okay, so
we will pick up with this tomorrow.
Let's see what דכל אימת דנפיק ליה. d'chol eimas d'nafik lei.